<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!--
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
	"file:///usr/share/sgml/docbook/dtd/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
-->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
	<articleinfo>
	<title>Localising GNOME Applications</title>
	<subtitle>So you want to translate GNOME?</subtitle>

	<authorgroup>
		<author>
		<firstname>Telsa</firstname><surname>Gwynne</surname>
		<!--
		<affiliation>
		<address>
		<email>hobbit@aloss.ukuu.org.uk</email>
		</address>
		</affiliation>
		-->
		</author>

		<author>
		<firstname>Dafydd</firstname><surname>Harries</surname>
		<!--
		<email>daf@muse.19inch.net</email>
		-->
		</author>
	</authorgroup>

	<copyright>
	<year>2003</year>
	<holder>Telsa Gwynne</holder>
	<holder>Dafydd Harries</holder>
	</copyright>

	<copyright>
	<year>2004</year>
	<holder>Dafydd Harries</holder>
	</copyright>

	<legalnotice id="legalnotice">
	<para>
	This document can be redistributed and/or modified under the terms of
	the GNU General Public License; either version 2 of the license, or
	(at your option) any later version. The full text of the license can
	be found at http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html.
	</para>
	</legalnotice>

	<revhistory>
	<revision>
		<revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
		<date>7th August 2003</date>
		<revdescription>
		<para>
		Started document.
		</para>
		</revdescription>
	</revision>

	<revision>
		<revnumber>0.2</revnumber>
		<date>15th August 2003</date>
		<revdescription>
		<para>
		Remembered we were supposed to be writing this. Added
		lots more sections and filled some in.
		</para>
		</revdescription>
	</revision>

	<revision>
		<revnumber>0.3</revnumber>
		<date>31st August 2003</date>
		<revdescription>
		<para>
		Filled in hints, bits about editors. Need more. Added two
		appendices.
		</para>
		</revdescription>
	</revision>

	<revision>
		<revnumber>0.4</revnumber>
		<date>02 September 2003</date>
		<revdescription>
		<para>
		Corrected some punctuation etc., added stub of new section
		"Dealing with changes".
		</para>
		</revdescription>
	</revision>

	<revision>
		<revnumber>0.5</revnumber>
		<date>17 November 2003</date>
		<revdescription>
		<para>
		Re-corrected some punctuation and stomped a few mis-spellings
		:) Added start of content for "dealing with changes". Added
		gedit to editor list. Added more FIXMEs.
		</para>
		</revdescription>
	</revision>

	<revision>
		<revnumber>0.6</revnumber>
		<date>4 January 2004</date>
		<revdescription>
		<para>
		Replaced a reference to <quote>gtk</quote> with one to
		<quote>gtk+</quote>, as that is the name of the CVS module.
		Put the document under the GPL. Added some information about
		creating and using compendia. Elaborated on the process of
		removing a <quote>fuzzy</quote> marker. Reformatted the
		document to 80 characters' width, and to use tabs rather than
		spaces for indentation. Replaced <quote>-</quote> and
		<quote>--</quote> with &amp;mdash; where appropriate. Added an
		example for the bit about translator_credits.
		</para>
		</revdescription>
	</revision>

	<revision>
		<revnumber>0.7</revnumber>
		<date>5 January 2004</date>
		<revdescription>
		<para>
		Reorganized the  bit about different methods and web
		interfaces. Added a link to the Chinese team's system, as
		suggested by Funda Wang. Added a note about GConf schema
		descriptions, as suggested by Åsmund Skjæveland. Added a link
		to the GPL.
		</para>
		</revdescription>
	</revision>

	<revision>
		<revnumber>0.8</revnumber>
		<date>19 January 2004</date>
		<revdescription>
		<para>
		Fix capitalisation in the title, and a typo.
		</para>
		</revdescription>
	</revision>
	</revhistory>
</articleinfo>

<abstract>
<para>
Notes on how to get started translating GNOME.
</para>
</abstract>

<sect1 id="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
GNOME programs are written with the intent of being localisable. This means
that a program can be augmented to behave in different ways in different
(physical) locations: printed pages in America will be a different size from
printed pages in Europe; weather temperatures will be displayed according to
Fahrenheit and Celsius scales in different places; and the language the user
sees from the program may be the user's native language.
</para>

<para>
Translation is a major part of this localisation process. The bulk of GNOME
translations are performed by native speakers on a volunteer basis. They take
sentences in the original English, supply the appropriate translation, and add
the file containing this information to the GNOME CVS repository so that the
next release of the software contains the new language.
</para>

<para>
This document tries to explain how to get involved in the translation process
for GNOME.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="finding">
<title>Finding your team</title>

<para>
First of all, is anyone working on your language already?
If so, they should be listed on the
<ulink type="http"
	url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gtp/teams.html">
	GNOME Translation Project team list</ulink>.
Contacting them is the first step.
</para>

<para>
If you have found a team for the language you with to localise to, but there
is no reponse from them, contact the <ulink type="http"
url="http://mail.gnome.org/mailman/listinfo/gnome-i18n">GNOME
Internationalisation mailing list</ulink>. Somebody there will advise you what
to do.
</para>

<para>
If there isn't a team for your language, you should also contact the mailing
list, in which case you will likely be invited to become the coordinator for
that language.
</para>

<para>
If you have successfully made contact with an active team, you can probably
safely skip the next section and move on to <xref
linkend="translating" />.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="founding">
<title>Founding a team</title>

<para>
So there isn't a team for your language, but you have bravely volunteered to
start one and be its coordinator? Well done!
</para>

<sect2 id="coord">
<title>The role of the coordinator</title>

<para>
As the coordinator for your team, you act as the primary contact person for
the team and are responsible for organizing the other translators in your
team. This includes attempting to prevent multiple translators simultaneously
attempting translations of the same file.
</para>

<para>
Coordinators need to be subscribed to the gnome-i18n mailing list. This is
highly recommended for all GNOME translators, but required of coordinators.
</para>

<para>
If any members of your team have CVS access, it will likely be you. If you
don't, each team member will send translations to you, and you will in turn
forward them to somebody with CVS access who will commit them.  This ensures
that all the right translations go to the right people at the right time.
</para>

<para>
Initially, at least, bugs pertaining to your translation team will come in
your direction. (You're not likely to get many bugs until your translation
becomes used.) Your language will have its own component in <ulink type="http"
url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org">GNOME's Bugzilla bug tracking system</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
The coordinator is often expected to deal with the more technical
aspects of translation work, such as plural forms, updating
configure.in files and generating POT files. (All of which will be
covered later. We hope.)
</para>

<para>
You might also be involved in recruiting more members into your
translation team. Many hands make the translations go faster, even
though it might mean more work for you!
</para>

<para>
It is also your responsibility as coordinator to stop being a coordinator when
it is appropriate: for example when you no longer have the time to dedicate to
the effort that it deserves. If you know that you will no longer be able to
perform the coordination role, ask someone to take your place in advance.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="lang-code">
<title>Language codes</title>

<para>
To begin with, you will need to find out what your language code is. This is a
two- or three-letter code. More popular languages will tend to have two-letter
codes, whereas more obscure languages will tend to get stuck with a
three-letter one. For languages spoken in more than one country, a translation
specific to a country will be followed by an underscore and the two-letter
country code capitalized. This can further be appended with an at-sign and
more qualifying information. For now, know that language codes typically look
like "fr" (French) or "en_GB" (English as used in Great Britain).
</para>

<para>
If you do not know what the code for your language is, try looking around to
see if there are translation efforts for other projects (such as <ulink
type="http" url="http://kde.org"><acronym>KDE</acronym></ulink>,
<ulink type="http" url="http://mozilla.org">Mozilla</ulink> and <ulink
type="http" url="http://openoffice.org">OpenOffice</ulink>) in your language
&mdash; these will (should) use the same code. If that doesn't turn up
anything, ask the mailing list for help.
</para>

<para>
GNOME uses standard codes as defined in
<!-- FIXME - do proper xref -->
<ulink type="http" url="http://www.w3.org/WAI/ER/IG/ert/iso639.htm"> ISO
standard 639</ulink> (for language codes) and <ulink type="http"
url="http://www.iso.ch/iso/en/prods-services/iso3166ma/02iso-3166-code-lists/list-en1.html">
ISO standard 3166</ulink> (for country codes). The gnome-i18n members will
help you identify your language code.
</para>

<para>
Your language code is used to identify your localisation, for example in the
names of locales and files. Once you have your code, you can start
translating.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="needs">
<title>What you will need to start</title>

<para>
There are a number of things that will help you immensely in your
translation work.
</para>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	<term>A mailing list</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	You need a forum where your group can talk, preferably in its own
	language. You can use it for monitoring who is translating what,
	discuss difficult words and terms, and hammer out a glossary. It
	might be appropriate to share this mailing list with a translation
	team for another project (e.g. KDE) It is also a good place to
	post announcements about your translation.
	</para>

	<para>
	The mailing list might also be used by users of your translations for
	giving feedback and general discussion.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	<term>A web site</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	A web site is good for introducing people to your effort, distributing
	work, keeping track of who's working on what, and keeping things like
	glossaries.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	<term>A glossary</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	It is important that your translation consistently uses the same
	terms to avoid confusing users. A standard glossary will help you
	ensure that you do not refer to one thing by many names. Try not to
	invent new terms but to reuse existing ones &mdash; look for a
	governing body for your language, or translations used in other
	projects, or terminology used in Microsoft Windows or Apple OS X. In
	particular, it's preferable to be consistent with other free desktop
	environments such as KDE. If you do have to create new terminology, or
	decide to use one word rather than another, do document your choice
	(and the reasoning behind it) in your glossary. This saves confusion
	later. Expect to change some of your initial glossary suggestions
	after some time translating. It's only once you start translating that
	you start to notice problems.
	</para>

	<para>
	Some teams are the same people as those translating KDE or Mozilla or
	OpenOffice into the same language. In other teams, there is a separate
	team for each of these projects. In the second case, it's a very good
	idea to contact these other teams and find out what they are using,
	what they have abandoned, and so on.
	</para>

	<para>
	A good foundation to base your glossary upon is a combination
	of the <ulink type="http"
	url="http://developer.gnome.org/documents/style-guide/wordlist.html">
	GNOME Documentation Project's Style Guide</ulink> and the glossary
	found in the gnome-i18n module, although the latter needs updating.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	<term>An IRC channel</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	This is a benefit for many of the same reasons as a mailing list is,
	except that it can be more convenient for certain kinds of discussion,
	especially for quick queries. It can also be good for helping users of
	your translation. The
	<ulink type="http" url="http://freenode.org">Freenode network</ulink>
	is an IRC network dedicated to free software-related discussion and
	would be a suitable place for hosting your channel.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	<term>The <application>gettext</application> tools</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	<application>gettext</application> is a package which contains
	tools for creating translatable strings, turning those strings
	into a list which can be translated, updating these strings,
	and converting them into a format the computer can use. Someone
	on your team (as many as possible really) needs these and to
	know the basics of how to use them.
	</para>

	<para>
	The package is installed by default on many Linux distributions.
	Where it is not installed, it is still usually available. 
	</para>

	<para>
	You should also look at <application>intltool</application>. This is
	rather like a front-end to gettext and performs some tasks you need to
	do as a Gnome translator. It is often available for your distribution,
	but it is almost always a release or two ahead of whatever is on your
	distribution. You can find it in Gnome CVS:
	<command>cvs checkout intltool</command>.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="translating">
<title>Translating</title>

<para>
This is where we get down to it. There are almost 17,000 distinct strings
which are found in the basic distribution of GNOME 2.4. This doesn't include
Evolution, Galeon, any IM client or other things which you may see as
necessary. There are a variety of tactics and methods you can employ, but they
all boil down to translating all those strings.
</para>

<sect2 id="approaches">
<title>Different approaches</title>

<para>
There are different ways of translating. Some teams simple parcel out the
<quote>po file</quote> to different people and the members work through them
with a text editor and return them to the person who can commit them into
GNOME. Other teams use web-based systems. All have advantages and
disadvantages.
</para>

<para>
<filename>.po</filename> file details are at the end of this page as the
longest section. You can jump ahead to the section on <link
linkend="po-files"><filename>.po</filename></link> files if you don't intend
to use anything else.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="web-interfaces">
<title>Web interfaces</title>

<para>
A web interface generally provides anyone with a list of strings and waits for
them to suggest translations for them. Someone periodically sweeps up all the
results and feeds them back into CVS. The advantage is that only the team
co-ordinator and the maintainer of the web interface need to care about how to
make <filename>.po</filename> files. This lets anyone who doesn't have GNOME,
a useful editor, or other things help with the translation. One disadvantage
is that without being able to see the rest of the file, contributors may not
realise how other people are translating applications. If your team is trying
to achieve consistency, this can be a problem. Another is that comments from
the developer to translators explaing the string are not always shown.
</para>

<para>
Existing web interfaces include the following:
</para>

<simplelist>
<member><ulink type="http" url="http://prevod.org">Prevod</ulink></member>
<member><ulink type="http"
url="http://www.kyfieithu.co.uk">Kyfieithu</ulink></member>
<member><ulink type="http" url="http://i18n.ricetons.com/">the Chinese team's
system</ulink> &mdash; you can log in with username <quote>i18n</quote> and no
password</member>
</simplelist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="po-files">
<title>po files</title>

<para>
There is an excellent document available about how to checkout <filename
class="directory">po/</filename> directories, create <filename
class="directory">.pot</filename> files, turn them into
<filename>.po</filename> files, and check them back into CVS:
<ulink type="http"
url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/tutorials/gnome-i18n/translator.html">
Using GNOME CVS as a Translator</ulink>. You must read this. It explains all
the details of using the <application>gettext</application> tools. Since this
is 90% of working with <filename>.po</filename> files, you need to know it. We
have not repeated it here. We have simply added a few comments which are in
addition to it. They do not replace it.
</para>

<para>
Note that you can obtain <filename>.po</filename> files from your language's
status pages on the Gnome Translation Project website. (See below). Sometimes
special characters (non-ASCII) can be garbled doing this, but it is a useful
alternative to CVS.
</para>

<para>
A <filename>.po</filename> file is simply a list of strings from the original
program, with spaces for you to put your version in. There is a set of headers
at the top, some of which you will have to edit. The Project-Id-Version will
become the name of the module. The POT-Creation-Date should be filled in
automatically. You must edit the PO-Revision-Date yourself. Language-Team
should be your team's language and ideally an email address which will contact
one or more of your members. The Content-Type <emphasis>must</emphasis> be
UTF-8 and you must make sure that the resulting file is in fact UTF-8 format.
On UNIX and UNIX-like systems, the <command>file</command> command will tell
you what format it is in. On a machine with all the
<application>gettext</application> facilities installed, you can use
<command>msgfmt -cv filename.po</command>. If the file is not UTF-8,
<command>msgfmt -cv</command> will produce an error message saying so.
</para>

<para>
You will meet comments in the file. When they say <quote>c-format</quote>,
this means that there are strings which the program will fill in itself. For
example, the clock applet in <application>gnome-applets</application> has a
string to translate of <quote>%H:%M</quote>. You can <quote>translate</quote>
this by pasting it straight in. They will be provided by the system clock on
the computer. %H is the hours. %M is the minutes.
</para>

<para>
There is a separate appendix on <link linkend="c-format-stuff">common C-format
strings</link>.
</para>

<para>
You will also meet messages to translators from the programmer. For example,
in <application>gnome-applets</application>, slightly after the message quoted
above you will find the comment <quote>translators: reverse the order of these
arguments if the time should come before the date on a clock in your
locale</quote>.
</para>

<para>
You will also have to replace menu accelerators: the keyboard shortcuts which
can be used instead of clicking on menus. Expect contradictions and collisions
in the early days. It is probably most important to do the accelerators for
<application>gtk+</application> first, since they will be in every single
GNOME application. Then you can use the remaining letters and try to work out
what combinations work the best. Don't worry if you have two or more menu
options with the same accelerator. As of 2.4, GNOME will let you cycle between
them.
</para>

<para>
You will often come across descriptions for <application>GConf</application>
keys. Usually, each key has both a short and a long description. Strings which
are key descriptions can be identified by the fact that they come from files
with names resembling <filename>.schemas.in.h</filename>.
</para>

<para>
When translating key descriptions, be careful with sample key values,
which will be enclosed in double quotes. They should not be
translated. For example:
</para>

<programlisting>
#: src/gnome-terminal.schemas.in.h:70
msgid ""
"Default color of terminal background, as a color specification (can be HTML-"
"style hex digits, or a color name such as \"red\")."
msgstr ""
"Rhagosodiad lliw cefndir y terfynell, fel penodid lliw (gall fod mewn hecs-"
"ddigidau fel yn HTML neu fel enw lliw megis \"red\")."
</programlisting>

<para>
In the example, <quote>red</quote> is a sample key value, and must be
copied verbatim into the translation. Note that because the double
quote character is significant in <filename>.po</filename> files, it
is escaped with the backslash.
</para>

<para>
If you meet English messages which you cannot understand, file a bug against
the application telling the developer of the problem. If you meet English
messages which you cannot reasonably translate, file a bug again. Translators
as a group file dozens and dozens of these, because translators are the ones
who spot them. The earlier you file these the better. When you learn what the
message means, you will probably forget about filing the bug. Filing them gets
them fixed, and stops other translators having to struggle with the strings.
</para>

<important>
	<title>Don't touch the msgid lines</title>
	<para>
	Do not edit the English strings in the file. If you do that, the
	programs for merging them into the main application will get confused.
	Your changes to the English strings will be lost, and your
	translations may not be incorporated.
	</para>
</important>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="changes">
<title>Dealing with changes</title>

<para>
Unfortunately, software changes, and that includes changes to the translatable
content of the software. Strings get added, strings are changed, and sometimes
strings are removed. Fortunately, there are tools and procedures which can
help you to keep up with changes to the software you're translating.
</para>

<sect2 id="status-table">
<title>The status tables</title>

<para>
Carlos Perelló Marín maintains status tables for each language translation in
GNOME. They are available in the
<ulink type="http" url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gtp/">Gnome
Translation Project</ulink> pages. The tables include several views and are
updated three times a day.
</para>

<simplelist>
	<member>
	<ulink type="http"
	url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gtp/status/">index
	page</ulink>
	</member>

	<member>
	<ulink type="http"
	url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gtp/status/gnome-2.6/essential.html">
	essential packages: all languages
	</ulink>
	</member>

	<member>
	<ulink type="http"
	url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gtp/status/gnome-2.6/full-info.html">
	all packages, by group: all languages
	</ulink>
	</member>
</simplelist>

<para>
For each language (follow a highlighted language for details) there are tables
showing the overall status and a breakdown by package. These tables contain
links to the latest <filename>.pot</filename> file (if the application has not
been translated at all to your language yet) or the latest
<filename>.po</filename> file (if a start has been made on the translation).
You can download these straight from the status pages instead of using CVS.
You can't upload them that way, but the download facility is very useful.
</para>

<para>
And all of this is maintained for the final release of Gnome 1 (Gnome 1.4),
the latest stable release, and for the packages which will become the next
stable release. At the time of writing (January 2004), 2.4 was the last stable
release and the 2.5 release, which will become 2.6, is under development.
</para>

<para>
As soon as translations for your language have been committed to CVS, your
language will acquire its own section in the status tables. You should
probably bookmark the pages relevant to your language. They are very very
useful.
</para>

<para>
Your language page will have a URL of the form
http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gtp/status/gnome-2.6/XX/index.html
where XX should be replaced by your language code (lower-case). The above URL
is for the releases that will become GNOME 2.6. If you want to see the stable
release of Gnome, adjust the URL accordingly.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="msgfmt">
<title>Updating changed packages</title>

<para>
You will generally discover changes when you update your copy of a module in
Gnome CVS or when you refresh your browser on your status pages. Again,
<ulink type="http"
url="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/tutorials/gnome-i18n/translator.html">
How to use GNOME cvs as a translator</ulink> is your guide to the necessary
cvs commands. If you know there are more strings to translate, then you need
to generate a new <filename>.pot</filename> file which contains all the
strings to translate and then to merge it with your <filename>xx.po</filename>
file which has a less up-to-date set of translated strings. Generate the
<filename>.pot</filename> file with <command>intltool-update --pot</command>.
Merge the two together with <command>msgmerge -o new-xx.po xx.po
.pot</command> and try very hard to get those in the right order!
</para>

<para>
FIXME: mention <command>intltool-update xx</command>
</para>

<para>
Then run <command>msgfmt -cv new-xx.po</command> to see how much work remains.
If you are lucky, there will be many many <quote>fuzzy</quote> strings:
strings which are so similar to already-translated messages that the msgfmt
program has suggested that you use the old translation for the new string.
</para>

<caution>
<title>Fuzzy translations are just that</title>
<para>
<command>msgmerge</command> gets fuzzy translations wrong from time to time.
Every translator has their favourite suggestion which was badly wrong: my
(Telsa's) personal favourite is the suggestion that the translation for
<quote>Open window</quote> should be used to translate <quote>Close
window</quote>...
</para>
</caution>

<para>
Go through your new file searching for instances of the string
<quote>fuzzy</quote>. If it is in a comment above a translation that looks
correct, then remove the word <quote>fuzzy</quote>. If <quote>fuzzy</quote> is
the only word on the line, you can safely remove the whole comment. If you do
not remove the word <quote>fuzzy</quote> then the translation will not be
used. For example:
</para>

<programlisting>
#, fuzzy
msgid "Blah blah blah."
msgfmt "La la la."
</programlisting>

<para>
In this case, if you are confident in the translaton, the line with "fuzzy" in
it can be removed entirely:
</para>

<programlisting>
msgid "Blah blah blah."
msgfmt "La la la."
</programlisting>

<para>
However, you may come across a something like this:
</para>

<programlisting>
#, c-format, fuzzy
msgid "Very important: %s"
msgstr "Pwysig iawn: %s"
</programlisting>

<para>
In this case, if you wish to remove the fuzziness, the "c-format" tag must be
left intact:
</para>

<programlisting>
#, c-format
msgid "Very important: %s"
msgstr "Pwysig iawn: %s"
</programlisting>

<para>
Sometimes a whole set of messages are moved to a new module. This can be
particularly disheartening if you had translated them once already and think
you now have to do them again. You can save on the work by using the
<filename>.po</filename> file from that module with
<command>msgmerge</command>. You can also generate yourself a compendium of
messages you have translated which you can keep, edit, and use as a source of
suggested translations. You can do this using <command>msgcat</command>, in
the form <command>msgcat a.po b.po c.po > compendium</command>. You should
check the contents of the compendium before using it for translation,
especially for strings of the form <quote>#-#-#-#-#</quote> which indicate
conflicts among the original <filename>.po</filename> files. This feature also
means that you can use <command>msgcat</command> to check for inconsistencies
among <filename>.po</filename> files. Once you have created your compendium
with <command>msgcat</command>, you can make use of it with
<command>msgfmt</command>, as you would any other <filename>.po</filename>
file.
</para>

<!-- FIXME: Daf, how do you make and use a compendium? -->

<para>
You may find that a whole selection of messages are no longer used in the
application. They will be moved down to the bottom of the
<filename>.po</filename> file and left there, commented-out. A
<keycap>#</keycap> at the start of a line comments it out. It is ignored.
Unless there is a very large number of these and they really are getting in
the way, do not delete these lines. They may come back into the application.
They can also be used by the <command>msgmerge</command> program as a source
for finding fuzzy translations. Leave them where they are.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="first-app">
<title>Choosing the first packages to translate</title>

<para>
Here are some factors which may help you decide what to translate first.
</para>

<para>
It is probably best to pick something very small the first time, in order to
get used to the translation tools you are using. It is also useful to pick
something which is an application rather than a library. This way, you will be
able to run the application and see what it looks like. So a small stand-alone
application is a good choice.
</para>

<para>
Unless you are running GNOME built from CVS on your machine, you are likely to
have the most recent stable release on it. Therefore, it is a good idea to
translate the appropriate version of the application. So if you have
<application>bug-buddy-2.4</application> on your machine, use the 2.4 branch
of the <application>bug-buddy</application> module in CVS. If you use a
different version, some of the strings will have changed, and when you test
it, you won't see all of your translations.
</para>

<para>
As soon as you test your application in its new language, you will almost
certainly notice that common buttons and dialogue buttons are still in
English. This is because they come from some of the libraries and are reused
all over GNOME. To get those into your language, you will need to look at
<application>gtk+</application>, <application>libgnome</application> and
particularly <application>libgnomeui</application>. These files contain some
very difficult strings, but you do not need to do them all yet. Just look for
the strings which consistently show up in dialogue boxes. This will help
immensely.
</para>

<para>
The <application>gtk</application> package is part of a grouping called
developer-libs. It contains about half of the strings in that group. Once you
have translated <application>gtk</application> you will see a huge jump in
your statistics.
</para>

<para>
Some strings used in the <application>Epiphany</application> web browser come
from Mozilla. So even when you have completed Epiphany, you may occasionally
meet messages supplied by Mozilla which are not translated. If there is a
Mozilla Language Pack for your language, you won't notice this. If there
isn't, there is not a lot you can do about it. (You can persuade a friend that
they want to translate Mozilla, of course..)
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="installing">
<title>Installing</title>

<para>
If you have a reasonably up-to-date version of GNOME on a computer to which
you have root access, you can test your translations on your machine and view
them in context. This is strongly to be recommended. The machine will need a
message object (<filename>.mo</filename>) file which you can create with the
<command>msgfmt -cv</command> command. Run that on your po file, and you will
find a file called <filename>messages.mo</filename> in the directory. This
should be placed in the
<filename class="directory">/usr/share/locale/<replaceable>XX</replaceable>/LC_MESSAGES/</filename>
directory (where <replaceable>XX</replaceable> is the code for your locale)
and given the name of the program. Examples might be
<filename>metacity.mo</filename> or <filename>nautilus.mo</filename>.
Sometimes the program name requires a version number on it. Unfortunately,
there is no easy way to work out what the name of the <filename>.mo</filename>
should be for a given package. You will need to look at already-existing
filenames in a sister directory to see what they use and copy those. Have a
look around the different locales in <filename
class="directory">/usr/share/locale/</filename> and you should find good
examples to copy.
</para>

<para>
Then run the application. Changing the .mo file will probably cause the
application to crash, so save your work first; and if you are putting a
<filename>gnome-terminal.mo</filename> there, make sure you are ready for the
crash :) Once the file is in place, the app will be fine. It's just the act of
updating the file which can cause problems.
</para>

<note>
<title>The locale needs to exist</title>
<para>
The above will only work if the locale exists on your computer. If it does
not, you will need to create it. This is simplest on Debian: there is a
command for it. The procedure varies on other distributions, unfortunately,
and is well outside the scope of this document. Patches are welcome. :)
</para>
</note>

<para>
Once you have figured out how to install your translations onto a machine,
pass the instructions out far and wide to people who might be interested in
testing them out. Other people always spot more mistakes than you can. They
may also be inspired to help!
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="testing">
<title>Testing</title>

<para>
Once you have large parts of your desktop completed, testing becomes vital.
This is where you start realising that one of you has used one word for
<quote>install</quote> and someone else has used another; or that that word
<quote>body</quote> was referring to something other than a human body.
</para>

<para>
The more testing you can do, or persuade your friends to do, the better.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="editors">
<title>Editors and editor tricks</title>

<para>
A number of editors have special modes for editing <filename>.po</filename>
files, and will drop you into the appropriate mode automatically.
</para>

<para>
Ensure that your editor is writing in UTF-8 format. If the file is not this
format, things in GNOME CVS will break.
</para>

<para>
Editors known to deal with UTF-8 well:
</para>

<simplelist>
<member>Emacs</member>
<member>Vim</member>
<member>GEdit</member>
</simplelist>

<para>
For <application>vim</application>, things we have found useful to put into
<filename>.vimrc</filename> are:
</para>

<programlisting>
set fileencodings=utf-8
" A vim macro that makes control-E copy the msgid to the msgstr:
map &lt;C-E&gt; :s/msgid "\(.*\)"\nmsgstr ""/msgid "\1"&lt;C-V&gt;&lt;CR&gt;msgstr "\1"/&lt;CR&gt;
</programlisting>

<para>
There is a plugin for editing <filename>.po</filename> files in vim which has
several other useful tricks. It is available on the <ulink type="http"
url="http://www.vim.org">Vim website</ulink> as, unsurprisingly,
<ulink type="http"
url="http://vim.sourceforge.net/scripts/script.php?script_id=695">
po.vim</ulink>
</para>

<para>
<application>GNU-Emacs</application> has an entire PO mode.
</para>

<para>
There is a program called <application>gtranslator</application> which helps
you translate applications and which is specifically designed for translating
GNOME.
</para>

<para>
Other people are welcome to fill in more tricks for editors, ideally as
dotfile instructions.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="other-hints">
<title>Other hints</title>

<para>
There are some things we have learned from bitter experience, and we are
including them here so other people don't do it.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
	<para>
	Don't leave it ages to get stuff on the branch. We fell for this.
	However long it takes to check out the branch and update your
	translation, and however painful it is, if you intend to do both HEAD
	and branch, apply the changes to both. If you don't, you will meet a
	day when you spend hours and hours and hours doing nothing but feeding
	stuff back onto the branch.
	</para>

	<para>
	If you are on a slow connection or a metered connection, check the
	branches out into a separate directory rather than flipping between
	branch and HEAD. It might take longer the first time, but it saves a
	lot of time in the long run.
	</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
	<para>
	Automate as much as is safely possible. For example, when you are
	adding new translations, you will type the same three lines into the
	main Changelog about adding your locale to
	<filename>configure.in</filename> something like fifty times. Make a
	file which says it all already, and update the date daily. And then
	just include it with an editor macro. It's a lot better than typing it
	in fifty times. Use shell aliases for frequently used commands. For
	example: <command>alias cy-commit='cvs commit -m "Updated Welsh
	translation." cy.po ChangeLog'</command>
	</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
	<para>
	Find a language enthusiast! You will meet all manner of strange
	strings to translate, from the detailed spreadsheet terminology of
	Gnumeric to your language's equivalent of the English <quote>The quick
	brown fox..</quote> sentence which is used in the font selector
	because it includes every English letter. You will need to find or
	invent your own alternative which contains the letters your language
	uses. (This may be harder for Japanese and Chinese...)
	</para>

	<para>
	If your language has an accepted set of translations of new
	terminology, be aware of it, even if you don't like it. Be prepared to
	justify why you didn't use some <quote>official</quote> terminology...
	</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
	<para>
	Expect the occasional deliberately silly string. You will meet
	in-jokes from GNOME hackers as you go through more and more files. The
	GEGL, for example, may be a code library, but it is also the
	abbreviation for Genetically Engineered Goat, Large, and is just a
	silly joke that crops up in various places in GNOME. There is no need
	to translate it. There is also a selection of bizarre
	<quote>hints</quote> in one of the aisleriot files.
	</para>

	<para>
	Accept them. Put up with them. They are part of what makes GNOME fun,
	although it's difficult to believe that when you've just worked your
	way through four dictionaries trying to work out what the word might
	be...
	</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
	<para>
	The gnome-i18n mailing list and the #i18n IRC channel can
	be either really busy (gnome-i18n) or almost always quiet
	(#i18n), but there are people on them who have almost certainly
	met these things before, and can suggest ways to deal with
	them. Use them.
	</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
	<para>
	It's really easy to omit the underscores which will turn a key into a
	keyboard shortcut in a menu. You can check whether the number of
	underscores in the msgids and the msgstrs match with the command
	<command>msgfmt --check-accelerators=_</command> (but note that once
	you have filled the translator_credits one in there will always be one
	that appears to be missing).
	</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
	<para>
	Test, test, test. Whilst it is hard to get everything localised on
	your machine, it is very easy to install your own latest translations
	for at least some applications. Do this. It will really help.
	</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
	<para>
	Create a tarball of completed translations. (Another good candidate
	for automation.) Put them up on the web with very simple walk-through
	steps which let other people install them. This gets you feedback (and
	help) much earlier than waiting for a distribution to ship them will.
	The instructions for installing will unfortunately differ for very
	nearly every distribution. But the results are worth it.
	</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<glossary>
<glossentry id="cvs">
	<glossterm>CVS</glossterm>
	<glossdef>
	<para>
	Concurrent Versioning System: the system used to maintain the
	repository of GNOME code in a central place.
	</para>
	</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="i18n">
	<glossterm>I18N</glossterm>
	<glossdef>
	<para>
	The abbreviation of internationalisation (the initial and final
	letters of the word and then eighteen letters between them): the
	process of ensuring a program comes in a form which can be localised.
	</para>
	</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="l10n">
	<glossterm>L10N</glossterm>
	<glossdef>
	<para>
	The abbreviation of localisation (the initial and final letters and
	then ten between them): the process of making a program work in a
	particular location. It includes both translating messages and
	tweaking such things as measurements, currency symbols and temperature
	scales.
	</para>
	</glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="locale">
	<glossterm>locale</glossterm>
	<glossdef>
	<para>
	FIXME
	</para>
	</glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossary>

<appendix id="gotchas">
<title>Special characters in po files, and one special string</title>

<para>
There is a separate appendix about <link linkend="c-format-stuff">C-format
strings</link>. Here is a list of other characters and situations which can
cause problems.
</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
	<term>Escape-able characters</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Some characters will be interpreted by the programs which operate on
	<filename>.po</filename> files and thus need to be escaped with a
	backslash in front of them.
	</para>

	<para>
	The most common character for this is a double-quote character like
	<keycap>"</keycap>.
	</para>
	</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term>Formatting marks</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	You may come across the combinations <literal>\n</literal> or
	<literal>\t</literal>. These mean newline and tab. You do not have to
	put the same number of these into your translation, but if there is
	one of these at the start (or end) of the string, you must include one
	at the start (or end) of your translated string.
	</para>
	</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term>Angle brackets and ampersands in GConf files</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	There are one or two modules where XML is used heavily. GConf is the
	most notable. XML treats the characters &lt;, &gt; and &amp; as
	special. You can not just include them in your translation. You must
	specify them as entities.
	</para>

	<simplelist>
	<member>&lt; is represented as &amp;lt;</member>
	<member>&gt; is represented as &amp;gt;</member>
	<member>&amp; is represented as &amp;amp;</member>
	</simplelist>

	<para>
	FIXME: I've sure we've met this. But where? And does
	it apply to all .in.in.h files too?
	</para>
	</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term>TRUE and FALSE</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	<quote>TRUE</quote> and <quote>FALSE</quote> show up in
	<application>gtk+</application> and in
	<application>Gconf</application> and in a lot of files generated by
	<application>Glade</application>. (These will have a name ending in
	<filename>.glade</filename>.) Do not translate them. Programs expect
	to see them and will be confused if they don't.
	</para>
	</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>
There is also one very special string in the <filename>.po</filename>
file: the msgid of <literal>translator_credits</literal>. This
will show up when someone running the application in your
language looks at the credits by following the
<menuchoice>
<guimenu>Help</guimenu>
<guisubmenu>About</guisubmenu>
</menuchoice>
path in the application. They will see a <guibutton>Translation</guibutton>
option. In that will be the contents of this
<literal>translator_credits</literal>. This is where you put your name(s), so
the world can see. The typical format is to put a list of names and email
addresses on separate lines, with the URL of any team page. For example:
</para>

<programlisting>
msgid "translator_credits"
msgstr
"Telsa Gwynne &lt;hobbit@aloss.ukuug.org.uk&gt;\n"
"Dafydd Harries &lt;daf@muse.19inch.net&gt;"
</programlisting>

<para>
Don't forget to do this one :)
</para>
</appendix>

<appendix id="c-format-stuff">
<title>Some C-format strings to leave alone &mdash; or to re-order</title>

<para>
This is a brief list of C-format strings you may need to know about.
</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
	<term>%s</term>
	<listitem>
	<para>This represents a string. An example is in nautilus:</para>
	<programlisting>
#: components/emblem/nautilus-emblem-view.c:834
#, c-format
msgid "The file '%s' does not appear to be a valid image."
msgstr ""
	</programlisting>
	</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>
Strings containing such C-format sequnces are marked with the "c-format" tag,
like in the example. Be aware that where there are two instances of one of
these, they are not necessarily the same string. Another nautilus example:
</para>

<programlisting>
#: components/hardware/nautilus-hardware-view.c:483
#, c-format
msgid "Uptime is %d days, %d hours, %d minutes"
msgstr ""
</programlisting>

<para>
If you need to re-arrange them to make them make sense, you can do that. In
English, this is common:

<programlisting>
#, c-format
msgid "%n out of %n"
</programlisting>

This might come out as <quote>10 out of 100</quote>. If your language wants to
say <quote>Out of 100, 10</quote>, you can reverse them like this:

<programlisting>
#, c-format
msgid "%n out of %n"
msgstr "Out of  %2$d, %1$d"
</programlisting>
</para>
</appendix>

</article>
